<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>CVS</site:title>
		<site:summary>How to use CVS to search for code changes, download the most recent iText source code and documentation.</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, download, CVS</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="1932111816">Open Source Development with CVS </site:book>
			<site:book asin="0596004591">Essential CVS </site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date$</site:updated>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
<div class="header">CVS Repository</div>
<div class="title">Concurrent Versions System</div>
CVS is the open standard for version control.
CVS provides the means to store not only the current version of a piece of source code, but a record of all changes (and who made those changes) that have occurred to that source code.<br />
See <a href="http://cvshome.org">cvshome.org</a> for more info:
<blockquote>CVS is the Concurrent Versions System, the dominant open-source
network-transparent version control system. CVS is useful for everyone
from individual developers to large, distributed teams:
<ul>
<li>Its client-server access method lets developers access the latest code from anywhere there's an Internet connection.</li>
<li>Its unreserved check-out model to version control avoids artificial conflicts common with the exclusive check-out model.</li>
<li>Its client tools are available on most platforms.</li>
</ul></blockquote>
<div class="title">Browse the CVS repository</div>
One of the most interesting features of CVS at SourceForge, is the ability to consult
<a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/itext/">the CVS repository</a> just using
your browser (no CVS client installation needed).
You can look for code that was removed; for instance if you used classes in
<a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/itext/src/com/lowagie/servlets/">package com.lowagie.servlets</a>
you can look in the CVS 'Attic' and download them from there if you still need them.
This can be useful to track down problems if you update from a very old version to
the most recent one. You can also look at the <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/itext/src/com/lowagie/text/Cell.java?r1=1.88&amp;r2=1.89">difference</a>
between one version and the other. This way, you can see what bugfixes and optimalizations were
added between versions.
<div class="title">Downloading iText from the CVS repository</div>
The iText repository is hosted at <a href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</a>.
You need CVS client software to be able to get the source from the CVS repository.
Please read the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=766&amp;group_id=1">WinCvs CVS Client Installation Instructions</a>
if you want to know how to obtain and install a CVS client. If you are new at using CVS,
you should also read the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=14033&amp;group_id=1">Basic Introduction to CVS and SourceForge.net (SF.net) Project CVS Services</a>.
In a tool such as WinCVS you will need to enter the servertype (pserver), the server
(cvs.sourceforge.net), a directory (/cvsroot/itext), a username (anonymous)
and maybe a password (just press the Enter key if prompted for it). This results in
the following CVSROOT: <span class="commandline">:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/itext</span>.<br /><br />
If you use CVS from the commandline, you'll have to login like this.
<div class="commandline">cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/itext login</div>
When asked for the <span class="commandline">CVS password:</span> just press enter.
You can obtain todays complete sourcecode tree using this statement:
<div class="commandline">cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/itext export -D now src</div>
The complete iText site, tutorial and examples are in another module:
<div class="commandline">cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/itext export -D now www</div>
<div class="title">Developer Access</div>
For the moment only 3 developers have been granted <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=15255">Developer CVS Access via SSH</a>.
They are the only ones allowed to commit changes to the CVS repository. All other users only have anonymous ReadOnly access.
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>