<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!-- $Header$ -->
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Documentation</site:title>
		<site:summary>How-to use iText. Where to find the tutorial and examples.</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, tutorial, examples, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="0596006551">PDF Hacks</site:book>
			<site:book asin="0321304748">PDF Reference (4th Edition)</site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date$</site:updated>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
<div class="header">Documentation</div>
<div class="title">API documentation</div>
For every new release the API documentation is automatically generated using
javadoc. You can consult the API <a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/docs/">online</a>
or download a <a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/downloads/docs.tar.gz">tar.gz</a> file with all the API documentation.
<div class="title">Tutorial and Code Samples</div>
There is a very old <a href="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/tutorial/index.html">tutorial</a> available, containing over a hundred examples.
The new tutorial (<a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/tutorial/">iText by Example</a>) is under construction.
Another good place to start, is the examples-xxx.zip available on
<a href="http://itextpdf.sourceforge.net/">Paulo's Early Access page</a>
(replace the xxx with the current early access release number).
<div class="title">Mailing-list</div>
iText has a very active mailing-list. If you don't want to
<a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/itext-questions">register</a>
rightaway, you can browse through the <a href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.lib.itext.general">mailing-list archives</a>
before sending your question to <a href="mailto:itext-questions@lists.sourceforge.net">itext-questions@lists.sourceforge.net</a>.
Try describing your problem as concrete as possible. We can't answer questions such as
"Why doesn't iText work on my computer". Please keep in mind that it is really difficult
for us to solve problems or track down bugs that we can't reproduce.
If possible, send us a small standalone source code example, demonstrating the
problem. Make sure we will be able to compile and execute it on our own virtual
machine (we probably don't have the same database systems, external libraries,
application servers,... you are using). Also send us the resulting PDF on your machine,
so that we can compare it with the PDF that is generated by us, using your code.
<div class="title">Third Party Presentations</div>
If you have written a presentation, a tutorial or some code samples you want
to share, please let me know and I'll add them here.<br />
<br />
If you want to start with a very simple example, Christoph Bartneck has written
you some pages on <a href="http://bartneck.de/work/id/designByNumbers/installationWindows.html">Step-by-step installation for Windows</a>
and <a href="http://bartneck.de/work/id/designByNumbers/creatingPDF.html">Creating PDF-files</a>.<br />
If you need more and if you are used to a Web Application environment,
<a href="http://www.cdjdn.com/downloads/itextexample.zip">Mark Stark</a>
has made a powerpoint presentation and a war file, introducing the generation of PDFs, filling/reading Acrobat forms
and deploying iText in a web application.<br />
Another interesting presentation is the powerpoint Sean Sullivan made for the Portland Java Users Group in Portland Oregon USA.
The topic was iText and PDF. You can download his PowerPoint slides <a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/downloads/pdf-itext-pjug-2003-05-27.ppt">here</a>
or you can read the <a href="http://www.onjava.com/pub/a/onjava/2003/06/18/dynamic_files.html">article</a>
he wrote for O'Reilly's <a href="http://www.onjava.com/">onJava.com</a>:
<a href="http://www.onjava.com/pub/a/onjava/2003/06/18/dynamic_files.html">Dynamically Creating PDFs in a Web Application</a>.<br />
<br />
For an introduction in German, I can refer you to an <a href="http://www.javamagazin.de/itr/online_artikel/psecom,id,441,nodeid,11.html">article
in JavaMagazin</a> by Cord Jastram. In a few selected examples, it gives you an overview
of some powerfull features such as generating an encrypted document, using PageEvents, generating Graphics, etc...<br />
Ilie Nae wrote a similar article in Romanian for NetReport:
<a href="http://www.agora.ro/netreport126/atelier1.shtml">Crearea de documente PDF in JAVA</a><br />
If you understand Portuguese and you are using iText in the context of a Web Application,
you can read the article <a href="http://www.cafeh.com.br/artigos/6/index.jsp">Como fazer um servlet gerador de relatorios PDF</a> by Pedro Burglin
at <a href="http://www.cafeh.com.br/">Cafeh.com.br</a>.<br />
<br />
There are some specialized examples around too: <a href="http://theserverside.com/">The Serverside</a> has an article on
<a href="http://theserverside.com/discussions/thread.tss?thread_id=26254">Inserting text to existing PDF file</a>.
There are examples available on making charts with <a href="http://www.jfree.org/jfreechart/">JFreeChart</a> and
<a href="http://cs.gmu.edu/~eclab/projects/mason/extensions/webtutorial1/">exporting</a> them to PDF.
If you want to use iText in a <a href="">ColdFusion</a> application, just read
<a href="http://cephas.net/blog/2004/03/14/using_itext_pdf_coldfusion.html">blog example</a> first.
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>