<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Direct Content</site:title>
		<site:summary>Add content directly to the PDF file using the PdfContentByte class.</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, examples, PdfContentByte, Graphics, absolute positions, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="0321304748">PDF Reference (4th Edition)</site:book>
			<site:keyword>PDF</site:keyword>
			<site:keyword>Coordinate Systems</site:keyword>
			<site:keyword>Algebra</site:keyword>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date$</site:updated>
		<site:author>Bruno Lowagie</site:author>
	</site:metadata>
	
	<site:examples>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="XandYcoordinates" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>XandY.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Puts some marks at specific X and Y coordinates; connects the marks with a line and puts some text next to the marks</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="UpsideDown" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>upsidedown.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Same example as above, but now the origin is in the upper left corner</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="AffineTransformation" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>affinetransformation.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Same example as above, but now the X and Y coordinates are scaled</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="Transformations" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>transformations.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Add a template using different transformation matrices</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="TransformImage" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>transformimage.pdf</site:result>
			<site:externalresource>hitchcock.png</site:externalresource>
			<site:description>Add an image using different transformation matrices</site:description>
		</site:example>
	</site:examples>
	
	<site:chapter>

	<site:section name="xycoordinates">
		<site:sectiontitle>The coordinate system</site:sectiontitle>
<div>
See PDF Reference Manual (version 1.6) p169:
<blockquote>Coordinate systems define the canvas on which all painting occurs.
They determine the position, orientation, and size of the text, graphics, and
images that appear on a page.</blockquote>
If you start a new page in PDF, the CTM (current transformation matrix)
maps positions from user coordinates to device coordinates. The origin of
the coordinate system is in the lower left corner of the page by default.
The x-axis is oriented horizontally to the right, the y-axis vertically
to the upper left corner. All measurements are done in points.
This is not an iText specific choice. All this is documented in the PDF Reference Manual,
section 4.2 Coordinate Systems.
<site:source class="XandYcoordinates" />
Remark: if you measure the locations on the page, you will see that the distances
measured from the bottom or the left side of the page are not always correct.
Adobe's print dialog has several options (like "fit to paper") that change
the printed result.
</div>
	</site:section>
	
	</site:chapter>

</site:page>