<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!-- $Header$ -->
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Download &amp; Compile</site:title>
		<site:summary>How-to download iText (sourcecode and released jars) and how to compile it.</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, download, compile, release, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="0764546600">Open Source: The Unauthorized White Papers</site:book>
			<site:book asin="0596005814">Understanding Open Source and Free Software Licensing </site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date$</site:updated>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
	<div class="header">Download &amp; Compile</div>
<div class="title">License Agreement</div>
iText is published under 2 different licenses: MPL and LGPL.<br /><br />
If you are a new user of iText, MPL is recommended (without the LGPL).
MPL is less strict than LGPL. Please read the
<a href="MPL-1.1.txt" class="normal">MPL license agreement</a>
before downloading and/or using iText.<br />
LGPL is maintained for backwarts compatibility only.
If you choose the LGPL, you need to mention the MPL as an alternative license.
Please read the <a href="lgpl.txt" class="normal">LGPL license agreement</a>
for more info.<br /><br />
This library is free and I want it to stay free: you can use it without paying
a fee; you don't need to register anywhere. Only keep in mind that agreeing
with the license is crucial to protect the software, its developers and its users.
Please read section 15 and 16 of the LGPLicense with special attention:
This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
any warranty. If you don't like free software, don't (ab)use it!<br /><br />
Some companies have a policy not to use Free / Open Source Software
without a license or a support contract. The iText developers can't and won't sell you
such a contract, but they have granted Leonard Rosenthol and his company
<a href="http://www.pdfsages.com/">PDF Sages</a> the right to sell licenses
and support contracts on a case per case basis.
There was no money involved in this deal; the developers of iText are not
on the paylist of PDF Sages.  The responsibility for these contracts lies
with PDF Sages, not with the developers Paulo Soares and/or Bruno Lowagie.
<div class="title">Current release</div>
The current release on this site is <site:releasenumber />. This is considered a STABLE release ( <site:releasedate />).
iText<site:releasenumber /> was based on the Early Access release itext-paulo-<site:earlyaccessnumber />.<br /><br />
<table align="center" border="1" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" width="80%">
	<tr><th colspan="5">Download the library:</th></tr>
	<tr>
		<td width="40%" class="small">Mirror</td>
		<td width="20%" class="small">Source code</td>
		<td width="20%" class="small">Compiled code</td>
		<td width="20%" class="small">Documentation</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td class="small">prdownloads @ Sourceforge</td>
		<td class="small"><site:releasesrc /></td>
		<td class="small"><site:releasejar /></td>
		<td class="small"><site:releasedocs /></td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td class="small">downloads @ itext.sourceforge.net</td>
		<td class="small"><a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/downloads/src.tar.gz">src.tar.gz</a> or <a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/downloads/src.zip">src.zip</a></td>
		<td class="small"><a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/downloads/iText.jar">iText.jar</a></td>
		<td class="small"><a href="http://itext.sourceforge.net/downloads/docs.tar.gz">docs.tar.gz</a></td>
	</tr>
</table><br />
If you download the source, jar or docs from prdownloads, you get the release number in the filename.
If you download it from itext.sourceforge.net, you get the plain filenames: you can replace the old
iText.jar with the new one without having to change your CLASSPATH. In any case: the content of
the files with and the ones without the release number is the same, so you can choose which one to download.<br /><br />
If you need a more recent release (because you need extra functionality or some specific bugfixes
that was added more recently), please go the the <a href="http://itextpdf.sourceforge.net/">Early Access</a>
site (maintained by Paulo Soares) and check the version number (probably itext-paulo-<site:earlyaccesspaulo />).
This itext-paulo-<site:earlyaccesspaulo /> corresponds with <site:earlyaccesssrc /> and <site:earlyaccessjar />.
To know the relation between the older version numbers of the release on this site and older versions
of the Early Access release, please consult the <a href="history.html">history overview</a>.<br /><br />
Another option to get the source code is to download it from the <a href="cvs.html">CVS repository</a>,
for instance using <a href="ant.html">ant getFromCvs</a>.
<div class="title">Compiling the source</div>
The iText jar is compiled with the JDK1.4.
If you are using an older JVM in your environment, you could experience some compatibility problems.
In this case it is better NOT to use the downloaded jar, but to compile the code yourself with your own JDK.
If you have a version older than the JDK1.2, you will have to download an adapted version of the source
code from the <a href="http://itextpdf.sourceforge.net/">Early Access</a> site, as well as the 'Collection'
classes from SUN. If you are using the JDK 1.2 or 1.3, you will probably need some extra J2EE jar for
the packages com.lowagie.text.xml and com.lowagie.text.html. If you don't need the XML/HTML stuff,
you can delete those packages.<br />
There are of course also some ANT scripts that will make getting and compiling the source a lot easier.
There is a separate page on <a href="ant.html">iText ANT scripts</a>.
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>