<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Home Page</site:title>
		<site:summary>iText is a JAVA library that can be used to generate complex PDF documents (with images, tables,...).</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, servlets, iText, generate, internet, documents, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="0201758393">PDF Reference: Version 1.4 (3rd Edition)</site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
		<div id="side">
			<div class="search">
				<div class="sidetitle">Search the Site:</div>
				<FORM ACTION="http://search.freefind.com/find.html" METHOD="GET"  target="_self">
					<select name="s">
						<option value="">Complete site</option>
						<option value="iText">The home pages</option>
						<option value="tutorial">The tutorial</option>
						<option value="examples">The examples</option>
						<option value="api">The API</option>
						<option value="source">The Source Code</option>
					</select>
					<br />
					<font size="1" face="arial,helvetica" >
						<INPUT TYPE="HIDDEN" NAME="id" SIZE="-1" VALUE="3425713" />
						<INPUT TYPE="HIDDEN" NAME="pageid" SIZE="-1" VALUE="r" />
						<INPUT TYPE="HIDDEN" NAME="mode" SIZE="-1" VALUE="ALL" />
						<INPUT type="HIDDEN" name="n" value="0" />
						<INPUT TYPE="TEXT" NAME="query" SIZE="15" />
						<INPUT TYPE="SUBMIT" VALUE=" Find " />
						<br />powered by <A HREF="http://www.freefind.com">FreeFind</A>
					</font>
				</FORM>
			</div>
			<div class="news">
				<div class="sidetitle">NEWS</div>
		        <b>Nov 14th 2004:</b>
				<br />Module 'www' in CVS was cleaned up, except for the RTF tutorial page. New tutorial pages are being written.<br />
				<b>Nov 12th 2004:</b>
				<br />The build.xml is being replaced by different ANT-scripts. The site/tutorial will be generated from XML using XSLT.<br />
				<br />
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="header">iText Homepage</div>
		<div class="title">Project description</div>
		iText is a library that allows you to generate PDF files on the fly.<br />
		<br />
		The iText classes are very useful for people who need to generate
		read-only, platform independent documents containing text, lists,
		tables and images. The library is especially useful in combination
		with Java<SUP>(TM)</SUP> technology-based Servlets: The look and feel of HTML
		is browser dependent; with iText and PDF you can control exactly
        how your servlet's output will look.<br />
		<br />
		iText requires JDK 1.2. It's available for free under a multiple license: MPL and LGPL.

		<DIV CLASS="title">Technical Requirements</DIV>
		In order to be able to use these classes you should be
		acquainted with JAVA (TM) programming.<br />
		You'll also need the following Software:<br />
		<ul>
		<li>The Java Development Kit (JDK) 1.2 (or any later version)
		from <a href="http://java.sun.com/">Sun Microsystems Incorporated</a>.<br />
		If for some reason the library should have to work with an
		earlier version of the JDK, you will have to download the
		1.1.x version maintained by Paulo Soares
		(you'll find the Source on his <A HREF="http://itextpdf.sourceforge.net/" CLASS="normal">site</A>).</li>
		<li>Adobe Acrobat Reader from Adobe Systems Incorporated:<br />
		<br />
		<A HREF="http://www.adobe.com/prodindex/acrobat/readstep.html" CLASS="normal">
		<IMG SRC="getacro.gif" BORDER="0" ALT="download Acrobat Reader" />
		</A>
		</li>
		</ul>
		<div class="title">Getting started with iText</div>
		There are three pages that are extremely important if you want to work with iText.<br />
		<ol>
		<li>The first is the <a href="tutorial/">list of features</a>. This list is limited.
		Not all of iText functionalities are listed, but it's a good place to start.
		If you click on one of the features you get some explanation and some examples
		on how to use these features. As you can read on the <a href="documentation.html">documentation</a>
		page, you will find lots of iText code samples, just by doing some simple Google searches.</li>
		<li>If the examples don't work or you experience some typical newbie problems,
		please consult the <a href="faq.html">Frequently Asked Questions</a> page.</li>
		<li>If you need something that isn't on the feature list, please check the
		<a href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.lib.itext.general">mailing-list archives</a>.
		Lots of features are yet to be documented, but most of the iText functionality
		has been commented in the mailing-list. If you have a problem that has not been
		dealt with yet (or that should be in the FAQ), you can post it to the
		<a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/itext-questions">mailing-list</a>.
		But it's always a good idea to check <a href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.lib.itext.general">archives</a>	first.
		</li>
		</ol>
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>